Register of the Vitaliano Bernardino Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Vitaliano Bernardino Papers,
1966-1979
78026
Bernardino, Vitaliano
12 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope (5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Writings and printed matter, relating to education in Southeast Asia.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
Access Points
Southeast Asia Ministers of Education Organization.; Education.; Education--Asia, Southeastern.; Asia, Southeastern.; Philippines.
Biographical Note
1908, January 26 Born, Morong, Rizal, Philippine Islands
1933 B.S.E., National University
1938 M.A., Education and Psychology, University of the Philippines
1949 Administrative and Executive Officer, UNESCO Consultative Educational Mission to the Philippines
1957 Ph.D., University of the Philippines
ca. 1960 Assistant Director of Public Schools
ca. 1966 Director of Public Schools
ca. 1967 Undersecretary of Education
ca. 1970 Executive Director, Philippine-American Educational Foundation
1975 Director, Southeast Asian Ministers of Education Secretariat
1979 President, Gregorio Araneta University Foundation
Scope and Content of Collection
Writings and printed matter, relating to education in Southeast Asia.
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1956-1971. (Box 1)
  Biographical writings, arranged alphabetically by author, and bibliographies.
  - Biographical writings (Box 1)
    - Balatbat, Ramon G. and Pat H. Gonzales, Local Book Publishing: A Basic Industry, The Booklover's Bulletin, vol. VII, no. 1, January 1964, p. 4, 27-28, 33. Printed copy. Interview and biographical sketch.
    - The Energetic and Dynamic Leader, Vitaliano Bernardino, Division Superintendent of Schools for Pangasinan, The Pangasinan Educator, vol. XI, no. 5, February - March, 1956, p. 6-8., Printed copy.
    - Portugal, Virginia, The Educational Views of Dr. Vitaliano Bernardino, MA thesis, University of the Philippines, 1971., Bound typescript. Bound carbon copy.
  - Bibliography of speeches, 1957-1968., Typescript.
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1939-1974. (Box 1-4)
  Books, articles, and speeches, arranged alphabectically by title.
  - Untitled, tribute to Jose Rizal (in Tagalog), n.d., Typescript. (Box 1)
  - The Asian Educationist and the Development Decade, speech, UNESCO Regional Centre for the Training of Teacher Educators, Manila, April 26, 1965., Mimeographed copy.
  - Athletic Activities Deserve Public Support, speech, Central Luzon Athletic Association Meet, n.d., Carbon copy.
  - Au Revoir But Not Goodbye, October 23, 1974., Carbon copy.
  - The Bane of Professional Stagnation, ca. 1968-1969., Carbon copy.
  - The Basic Plan of the Philippine Educational System ca. 1968-1969., Carbon copy.
  - The Birth of the Pasay City Chapter, Order of the Knights of Rizal, ca. 1968-1969., Carbon copy.
  - A Bold and Decisive Approach to the Language Problem, speech, Benitez Memorial Lecture, January 10, 1969., Carbon copy.
  - Bold and Imaginative Measures in Education, General Education Journal, vol. II, nr. 4, 1967-1968, p. 32-39, 58., Printed copy.
  - Boy Scouting and the Rotary, speech, Rotary Club of Manila, October 31, 1968., Two carbon copies.
  - The Bureau of Public Schools in Community Beautification, speech, n.d., Carbon copy.
  - The Challenge of Economic Development of Education, speech, Rizal National Oratorical Contest, University of the East, March 26, 1965., Carbon copy.
  - The Challenge of Nationalism speech, commencement, Dagupan Colleges March 196, 1960., Three carbon copies.
  - Characteristics of Philippine Education, speech, ca. 1968., Carbon copy.
  - The Church and Population Control, ca. 1974., Carbon copy.
  - A College Graduate Looks to the Future, commencement address, Central Mindanao Colleges, April 18, 1969., Two carbon copies.
  - Commencement Address, speech, Fourth Commencement Exercises, Manila Science High School, ca. 1967., Typescript.
  - Commencement Speech, School for the Deaf and Blind, April 20, 1968., Typescript and carbon copy.
  - Comments on the SINCO REPORT, submitted to the Board of National Education, Manila, December 22, 1961., Mimeographed copy. (Box 2)
  - Community Education: A Social Invention, Speech, Seminar for Adult and Community Education Supervisors, Bayambang, Pangasinan, February 9, 1960., Mimeographed pamphlet.
  - Coordination of the PNRC Safety Program with those of Schools, Welfare and Civic Organizations, speech, ca. 1966., Carbon copy.
  - The Crises in Philippine Education, ca. 1968-1969., Carbon copy.
  - Current Trends in Philippine Education speech, May 11, 1972., Carbon copy.
  - Developing Moral Values Through Education, ca. 1974., Carbon copy.
  - Developments in Philippine Education, UNESCO: Philippines, vol. IV, nr. 10 & 11, October - November, 1965, p. 310-327., Printed copy.
  - The Dilemma of Philippine Education, Manila Times, August 13 - 17, 1963., Newspaper clippings and mimeographed pamphlet.
  - A Dream Realized, ca. 1972-1973., Two carbon copies.
  - Dynamics of Management in School Administration, outline, n.d., Two carbon copies.
  - Editorial re modernization of education, ca. 1972-1973., Two carbon copies.
  - Editorial re Boy Scouts, ca. 1972-1973., Carbon copy.
  - Education and Philippine-American Relations, speech, Kent State University, ca. 1967., Two carbon copies.
  - Education and the New Constitution, speech, Benitez Memoria Lecture Series, University of the Philippines, September 14, 1974., Annotated typescript, carbon copy of revised version, and press release.
  - Education Trends: Work Education, n.d., Carbon copy.
  - Educational Administration in a Scientific Age, speech, College of Education, University of the Philippines, September 30, 1967.
  - The Educational Factors of Economic Development, speech, n.d., Typescript and carbon copy.
  - Educational Ideas of Dean Francisco Benitez, ca. 1972-1973., Three carbon copies.
  - Educational Planning for National Development, speech, PPSTA Seminar on Educational Planning, Quezon City, January 17, 1967., Carbon copy.
  - Educational Reforms Under the New Society, four part series of articles, May 1973., Carbon copies.
  - An Estimate of My Co-Worker and Friend, Estanislao Lopez, March 11, 1960., Carbon copy and cover letter.
  - Excellence in Education (A Keynote Speech), University of the Philippines, 1966., Typescript.
  - Expanding the Dimensions of Education Through the Fulbrighters, speech, 1966., Two carbon copies.
  - The Filipino Women and Adult Education, speech, Annual Convention of the National Federation of Women's Club, May 5, 1966., Typescript.
  - Financing the Public Schools (with Manuel Lopez), Education in the Philippines, Chapter IX, edited by Antonio Isidro et al., Manila, University of the Philippines, 1939., Reprint of Chapter IX.
  - The Future Filipino: A Polyglot, ca. 1972-1973., Two carbon copies.
  - The Future of Philippine Education, ca. 1972-1973., Two carbon copies.
  - The Garden Movement and Community Beautification, speech, 1968., Carbon copy.
  - Goals of the Director and his Staff 1965-1966, October 1965., Mimeographed pamphlet.
  - A Handbook on Teaching Nationalism in the Elementary Grades (with Canuto P. Casim), Niesca Enterprises, Inc., 1962.
  - In-Service Training of Primary School Teachers in the Philippines, speech and bibliography, Symposium on the In-Service Training of Primary School Teachers in Asia, Manila, July 5 - 19, 1965., Two carbon copies.
  - Integrating Scientific and Technological Manpower Development into the National Economic Development Program in the Philippines, speech, National Science Development Board, December 11, 1965., Two carbon copies.
  - Issues in Education for Development, speech, Conference on Reforms and Innovations in Education for Development, Philippine Women's University, September 11, 1973., Mimeographed and carbon copies.
  - Language Development in the New Society, ca. 1974., Carbon copy.
  - Language in Philippine Education: Past, Present and Future, ca. 1972-1973., Carbon copy.
  - Leadership and the Leader, speech outline, ca. 1968., Carbon copy.
  - Let Us Have Faith in Ourselves, speech, Seminar for Adult and Community Education Supervisors, PUNCTC Bayambang, Pangasinan, February 9, 1960., Mimeographed pamphlet.
  - Meeting Outside Pressures on Education, Participant Journal, vol. 1, nr. 4, December 1970, p. 34-45., Printed and carbon copies, cover letter.
  - Message re agricultural and industrial fair, Province of Bataan, February 17, 1960., Carbon copy and letter of request.
  - Message re Bulacan Home Economics Association, July 8, 1969., Two carbon copies.
  - Message re Community College (TCMC), n.d., Carbon copy.
  - Message re First National Youth Hiking Competition, April 24, 1968., Two carbon copies and memorandum.
  - Message re Knights of Rizal Nationwide Educational and Fund Campaign, ca. 1968., Carbon copy.
  - Message re Monument to Rizal, December 9, 1968., Carbon copy.
  - Message re Seminar on Rizal, ca. 1968., Carbon copy.
  - Message re Thirteenth National Conference of the Catholic Education Association of the Philippines, n.d., Carbon copy
  - Message re Villamor High School celebration, January 25, 1960., Carbon copy and letter of request.
  - The National College Entrance Examination: A Landmark in Philippine Education, May 1974., Carbon copy.
  - Nationalism, the Call of the Hour, May 16, 1965., Three carbon copies.
  - The Need for Rizal Today, speech, 1965., Typescript and two carbon copies.
  - Needed Directions in Secondary Education, speech, Conference of FAO Fellows Association, Cebu City, May 22, 1969., Two carbon copies.
  - The New Administrative Structure of Philippine Education, December 1972., Two carbon copies.
  - New Concepts in School Education, speech outline, Saint Louis University, Baguio City, May 12, 1975., Typescript and cover letter.
  - Non-Governmental Organizations and Adult Education in the Philippines, speech, n.d., Mimeographed copy.
  - On Educational Leadership, speech, conference, Oroquieta, Misamis Occidental, April 19, 1965., Mimeographed copy.
  - Our Educational-Economic Paradox and the Filipino Youth, speech, Union High School, Manila, May 11, 1966., Carbon copy.
  - Our Unstable School Language Situation, ca. 1972-1973., Two carbon copies.
  - Outgoing President's Report, 1964-1966, College of Education Alumni Association, University of the Philippines, 1966., Carbon copy.
  - Outline of Keynote Speech, National Red Cross Convention, ca. 1968-1969., Carbon copy.
  - The Philippine Community School, doctoral dissertation, University of the Philippines, Quezon City, April 1957., Bound carbon copy.
  - The Philippine Fulbright Program, ca. 1972-1973., Two carbon copies.
  - The Philippine Language Problem Today, speech, First National Convention of the Linguistic Society of the Philippines, April 24-25, 1970., Carbon copy.
  - Philippine Social Life (with Sarafin E. Macaraig and Socorro C. Espiritu), Macaraig Publishing Company, Manila, 1956., Printed copy.
  - The Philippine-American Educational Exchange Program, speech, Rotary Club, Mandaluyong, April 5, 1974., Carbon copy. (Box 4)
  - The Philippines: An Economic and Educational Paradox, ca. 1965., Mimeographed copy.
  - Points Stressed During the Conference with Supervisors, Principals, Head Teachers at Boac North Central School, speech summary, August 30, 1965., Mimeographed copy.
  - Politics and Education in South Asia, ca. 1972-1973., Two carbon copies.
  - President Marcos, Mrs. Marcos, Fellow Scouters, and Friends of Scouting, ca. 1972-1973., Annotated typescript.
  - Press release re language of instruction in public schools, n.d., Three mimeographed copies.
  - The Problem of Our Youth Today, speech, NYWCC, August 8, 1966., Typescript.
  - The Problem of Public School Financing, The Manila Times, March 1972., Three carbon copies and cover letter.
  - Problems of Physical Education, speech outline, University of the East, Manila, April 22, 1967., Carbon copy and cover letter.
  - Pupil Dropouts: A Problem and a Challenge, speech, n.d., Carbon copy.
  - Qualifications of Teachers in Family Life Education, speech Asian Social Institute, Manila, May 29, 1968., Carbon copy and cover letter.
  - Quality Performance from Quality Teachers, speech, 1965., Typescript.
  - Remarks of the Supreme Commander, speech, Order of the Knights of Rizal, annual meeting, February 11, 1968., Two mimeographed copies.
  - Responsibility of high School Graduates, speech, ca. 1968-1969., Carbon copy.
  - Resuscitate the Philippine Community School, ca. 1972-1973., Carbon copy.
  - Revised Educational System and Local Leadership, speech, 47th Annual Convention of School Superintendents, Baguio, May 11, 1957., Mimeographed copy.
  - Rizal and Democratic Values, speech, ca. 1965., Carbon and mimeographed copies.
  - Rizal and Education, speech, Pasay City Chapter, Knights of Rizal, July 24, 1960., Typescript and carbon copy.
  - Rizal's Relevance Today, speech, ca. 1965., Two carbon copies.
  - The Role of Athletics in a Democracy, speech, Southern Tagalog Athletic Association Meet, Pasig, Rizal, February 6, 1966., Mimeographed copy.
  - The Role of Civic Organizations in Community Recreations, speech, Symposium on Community Involvement in Recreation, YMCA, Manila, April 15, 1972., Typescript and carbon copy.
  - The Role of Education in Rural Development, speech and bibliography, Seminar on Educational Planning for Rural Development in Southeast Asia, Bangkok, September 7, 1967., Mimeographed and carbon copies.
  - The Role of Public Schools in the Community-School Environmental Sanitation Program, speech, Convention of the League of Public Health Engineers, Manila, May 3, 1966., Carbon copy.
  - The Rotary Foundation, speech, ca. 1966., Carbon copy.
  - The Rotary Foundation Program and We, ca. 1965., Two carbon copies.
  - School Calendar Change Necessary, The Manila Times, March 22, 1963., Newspaper clipping.
  - The School Superintendent and Moral Regeneration, speech, School Superintendents' Convention, May 12, 1964., Mimeographed copy.
  - A Searching Look into the Problems of Education, speech, March 1966., Annotated typescript and cover letter.
  - The Secondary Graduate Looks to the Future, speech, commencement Jose Abad Santos High School, May 21, 1965, Morong High School, April 17, 1968., Two typescripts and two carbon copies.
  - Significance of the Conference, Directions for Philippine Education in the Seventies: Proceedings and Papers, National Conference on Education, Makati, Rizal, June 6 - 7, 1970, p. 3 - 4., Printed copy.
  - Some Imperatives of Public School Administration in the Philippines, speech, Golden Jubilee of the Superintendents Convention, Baguio City, May 14, 1959., Mimeographed copy.
  - Speech at the 57th Annual Convention of School Superintendents, Baguio City, May 23, 1966., Partial mimeographed copy.
  - The Status of Philippine Education, ca. 1967., Carbon copy.
  - Strategies for the Filipino School Superintendent, speech, Superintendents' Convention, Baguio City, May 10, 1965., Carbon copy.
  - Strategies of Effective School Management, speech outline, Seminar, Philippine Center for Professional Management, November 1968., Typescript, carbon copy, and letter of invitation.
  - Striving for Quality, Manila, Bureau of Public Schools, 1962., Mimeographed copy.
  - Teacher Education and the Challenge of the Future, February 1974., Two carbon copies.
  - Things I can Do for Education and the Teachers If and When Elected, speech. 1966., Carbon copy.
  - Today's Challegnes to Public School Administrators, speech, Convention of School Superintendents, Baguio City, April 19, 1958., Mimeographed copy.
  - Twenty-Five Years of Education Under the Republic, July 1972., Carbon copy.
  - Universal Literacy and the New Society, January 1974., Two carbon copies.
  - The USEF/P: Agency for Philippine Progress, 1968., Two carbon copies.
  - Vitalizing the School Program for Character Education, speech, Seminar on Character Education, Manila, February 5, 1968., Two carbon copies.
  - Welcome address, Confederation of Government Employees Organizations, June 23, 1966., Two carbon copies.
  - Welcome address, Phi Delta Kappa, March 18, 1968., Three typescript and three carbon copies.
  - What is the Matter with Philippine Education? speech, Ateneo de Naga, January 7, 1967., Mimeographed and carbon copies.
  - What is Wrong with Philippine Education, ca. 1966., Annotated typescript.
  - Women in Education in Asia, ca. 1967., Carbon copy.
  - Youth and a Better World, speech, ROTC, Fort Magsaysay, Nueva Ecija, June 9, 1968., Carbon copy.
  - The Youth and Our Ambivalent Society, speech, April 7, 1969., Typescript.
  - Miscellany.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1951-1977. (Box 5-9)
  Printed matter, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Community-School Movement of the Philippines (Box 5)
    - Aguilar, Jose, V., This Is Our Community School, Manila, Bookman, 1951., Printed copy.
    - Asuncion, Amparo, et al., The Philippine Community School, Quezon City, Bookman, 1956., Printed copy.
    - Corpuz, Isaac B., Sofronio S. Padre, and Eduardo Q. Dralin, ed., Evaluating Our Community Schools, Dagupan City: Mendoza, 1957., Printed copy.
    - Fleege, Urban H., The Community School: Potentialities and Needs, Bayambang, Philippine-UNESCO National Community School Training Center, 1956., Bound Mimeographed copy.
    - Fresnoza, Florencio, The Philippine Community School Training Center at Bayambang, Manila, Bureau of Printing, 1956., Two printed copies.
    - Laya, J.C., Little Democracies, revised edition, Manila, Inang Wika, 1951., Printed copy.
    - Laya, J.C., New Schools (For the Little Democracies), Manila, Inang Wika, 1951., Printed copy.
    - Orata, Pedro T., Community Education Abroad, Manila, UNRSCO Philippine Educational Foundation, 1954., Printed copy.
    - Payaual, Rafael B. and Diosdado G. Jimenez, Folk Schools in Adult Education, Manila, Bureau of Public Schools, 1959., Mimeographed copy.
    - Philippine Association of School Superintendents, Quarterly Bulletin., Printed copies.
      - Community Development Programmes in the Philippines, vol. IV, nr. 2, December 1954.
      - The Community School Program for Economic Development, vol. II, nr. 4, June 1953.
      - The Community School Program for Moral and Civic Education, vol. IV, nr. 1, September 1954.
      - The Evaluation of Community School Programs, vol. III, nr. 4, June 1954.
      - An Evaluation of the Philippine Community School School for the Last Five Years, vol. IV, nr. 4, June 1955.
      - The First Philippine National Training Program in Community Education Leadership, vol. IV, nr. 3, March 1955.
      - Home Economics in the Community-School Program, vol. III, nr. 3, March 1954. (Box 6)
      - Learning the Problems of the Community School, vol. I, nr. 1, September 1951., Two printed copies.
    - Philippine Islands, Bureau of Public Schools
      - The Community School of the Philippines, Manila, Bureau of Printing, 1957., Printed copy.
      - Evaluating the Iloilo Community School Program, Manila, Bureau of Printing, 1954., Printed copy.
      - Improving the Community-School Program: A Report of the Second Educational Work-Conference, Malolos, 1951., Printed copy.
      - It Can Be Done: Community Schools of the Philippines, Manila, Bureau of Printing, 1954., Printed copy.
      - Objectives in Adult and Community Education for the School Year 1962-1963, Manila, 1962., Bound mimeographed copy.
      - The Philippine Community School Bulletin, vol. XIV, nr. 6, November - December 1956., Printed copy.
      - The Philippine Community School Bulletin, "Parent Education Issue," vol. XIV, nr. 5, September - October 1956., Bound mimeographed copy.
      - The Philippine Folk School, Manila, Bureau of Printing, 1962., Printed copy.
      - The Role of Physical Education in a Community School, September 1961., Printed copy.
      - Strengthening Basic Learnings in the Community School: A Report of the 1960 Educational Work Conference, Ilagan, Isabela, 1960., Printed copy.
    - University of the Philippines, Institute on the Community School, Lectures on the Community School, Manila, 1952., Bound mimeographed copy.
  - Medicine. Campos, Paulo C., M.D., Challenge and Response in the Health Sciences Field, speech, University of the Philippines, Summer Institute, Baguio City, July 8, 1966., Mimeographed copy and cover letter. (Box 7)
  - Phi Delta Kappa. Correspondence, minutes of meetings, and by-laws, 1967-1968, 1973-1974. Arranged in chronological order.
  - Philippine Public Schools
    - Boquiren, Telesforo N., Educational Planning and the Philippine Experience, speech, n.d., Carbon copy.
    - Pascual, Dolores M., The Education for the Blind in the Philippines, speech, Regional Work Conference, Polo, Bulacan, November 16, 1965., Mimeographed copy, hand-outs, and cover letter.
    - Today's Investment in Tommorrow, Manila, 1960., Printed copy.
  - Rotary International. Know Your Community, 1960., Printed copy.
  - Southeast Asian Ministers of Education Organization. Arranged chronologically.
    - Education: The Challenge and Promise of Southeast Asia / SEAMEO, n.d., Printed copy.
    - Technical Workshop: Final Report, Southeast Asian Ministers of Education Secretariat, Kuala Lumpur, July 1966., Bound mimeographed copy.
    - Meeting of the Select Committee on The SEAMES Office: Final Report, Southeast Asian Ministers of Education Secretatiat, Bangkok, October 17 - 21, 1966., Bound mimeographed copy.
    - Compendium of Feasibility Team and Task Force Reports, Southeast Asian Ministers of Education Secretariat, Bangkok, November 1966., Bound mimeographed copy.
    - Presentation of the SEAMES Project Proposals, Second Conference, SEAMEO, Manila, November 25 - 28, 1966., Bound mimeographed copies.
      - Copy I.
      - Copy II.
    - Second Conference of the Southeast Asian Ministers of Education: Draft, Final Report, Manila, November 25 - 28, 1966., Bound mimeographed copy.
    - Second Conference of the Southeast Asian Ministers of Education: Final Report., Bound mimeographed copies.
      - Copy I.
      - Copy II.
    - The First Meeting of the Ministerial Committee on the Premanent SEAMES: Report, Kuala Lumpur, February 16 - 17, 1967., Mimeographed copy. (Box 8)
    - The Second Meeting of the Ministerial Committee on the Permanent SEAMES: Report, Singapore, May 18 - 19 1967., Bound mimeographed copy.
    - Southeast Asian Regional Seminar on Manpower Development and Educational Planning, Bangkok, September 4 - 9, 1967., Bound mimeographed copy.
      - Copy I.
      - Copy II.
    - Fourth Conference of the Southeast Asian Ministers of Education Council: Final Report, Djakarta, January 7 - 10, 1969., Bound mimeographed copy.
    - Extraordinary Session of the Southeast Asian Ministers of Education Council: Final Report, Bangkok, May 12 - 14, 1970.
    - Report of SEAMEO Brainstorming Session, Bangkok, September 2 - 4, 1970., Printed copy.
    - SEAMEO/SEADAG Seminar on Non-Formal Education: Final Report, Penang, October 11 - 14, 1971., Printed copy.
    - Post-War Development of the Lower Mekong Delta, SEARCA, College, Laguna, November 15, 1973., Mimeographed copy.
    - SEAMEO Charter, Bangkok, September 1973., Printed copy.
    - Beyond School Walls: A Study of Non-Formal Education in the SEAMEO Region, Bangkok, 1973-1974., Printed copy.
    - Preliminary Meeting on SEAMEO's Role in Post-War Educational Development in Khmer Republic, Laos and the Republic of Viet Nam: Draft, Final Report, Saigon, January 9 - 11, 1974., Mimeographed copy.
    - A Study of Non-Fromal Education in the SEAMEO Region, 1973-1974:Summary Report, Bangkok, October 1974., Printed copy.
    - Annual Director's Report, SEAMES, 1975., Printed copy. (Box 9)
    - Regional Conference on Non-Formal Education: Final Report Bangkok, August 16 - 21, 1976.